A Guide to the J. B. Williams Company Records 1967.0001
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
J. B. Williams Company Records
1853-1956
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1967.0001
85 Linear Feet
Started as Williams' Genuine Yankee Soap around 1840; moved to Glastonbury, Connecticut in 1847 and gained its current name in 1848; acquired Conti Products Corporation in 1950; acquired R. B. Selmer, Inc. in 1952; was acquired by Pharmaceuticals, Inc. in 1957 and moved to Cranford, New Jersey but keeping the same name; was eventually sold to Nabisco in 1971.
History
James Baker Williams was born in 1818 in Lebanon, Connecticut. He was educated in Manchester, Connecticut, and, in 1834, began employment with F. and H.C. Woodbridge, a general store located in Manchester. Williams was offered half-interest in the store in 1838, after which its name was changed to Keeny and Williams. Two years later, Williams sold his interest in the store, but retained his share in the drug department. He began experimenting with various soaps to determine which were best for shaving, and eventually developed Williams' Genuine Yankee Soap, the first manufactured soap for use in shaving mugs.
In 1847, Williams moved his enterprise to a rented gristmill on William Street in Glastonbury, Connecticut, where he continued to manufacture shaving soap and a few other products. His brother, William S. Williams, joined the firm around 1848, and it was at this time that the firm's name was changed to the James B. Williams and Company.
William's shaving soaps were sold throughout the United States and Canada, and as a result of rising demand, the facilities were expanded several times in the late 1800s. In 1885, a joint stock company under the name of J. B. Williams Company was formed under the laws of the state of Connecticut. James Williams supervised many aspects of the company until shortly before his death in 1907 at the age of eighty-eight. The Williams family continued to manage the company until it was sold in 1957.
By the early 1900s, the company was known throughout the world. In addition to its line of shaving creams, the firm produced talcum powder, toilet soaps, and other toilet preparations, eventually developing such as Aqua Velva, Lectric Shave, and Skol. In 1950, the company merged with Conti Products Corporation of Brooklyn, New York, and took over its entire line of products, including Conti Castile Soap. A 1952 merger with R.B. Selmer, Inc. added Kreml Hair Tonic and Kreml Shampoo to the company's list of products.
In 1957, a New York based conglomerate, Pharmaceuticals, Inc., acquired the J.B. Williams Company. The new owner, maker of Geritol, Serutan and Sominex, moved the Williams Company to Cranford, New Jersey in 1960, adopting the name J.B. Williams Company.
The J.B. Williams' plant in Connecticut was taken over by ten former Williams' employees who wanted to preserve the old soap-making process, and became Glastonbury Toiletries. The firm made shaving soaps, bathroom soaps, castile soap, aerosol shaving creams, body lotions, and shampoos. Its largest contract was with the J.B. Williams Company.
In 1971, the J.B. Williams Company was sold to Nabisco, and in 1977, Glastonbury Toiletries closed. The original 1847 factory is still standing, and, in 1979, was converted into a condominium complex. I In 1983 it was placed on the National Register of Historic Places.
Scope and Content
The records of the J.B. Williams Company provide information on a company known for its manufacture of fine men's toiletries. The records also provide some bibliographical information on the company's founder, James Baker Williams (1818-1907), and his family.
The bulk of the records are from the period 1850 to 1930 when the company was still a family owned and operated enterprise. Records pertaining to the post-1930 period, during which the company expanded and was eventually sold, are limited. The majority of the records are bound volumes which record the general business of the company such as accounting records, purchasing records, sales records, and overseas sales records.
A small amount of administrative records give a more intimate view of the company's history. In addition, the records contain scrapbooks and advertisements which give an excellent example of the types of promotional campaigns popular in the United States at that time. Many of these advertisements contain drawings or photographs from the 1930s and 1940s of important athletes from a variety of sports including baseball, football, boxing, and track and field. There is, however, only a small amount of personal and biographical information and correspondence concerning James B. Williams and his family.
Arrangement
Series I: Administrative Records ( 1888-1956 ) contains a small amount of records concerning the administrative and financial running of the company. These records include correspondence, annual reports, company newsletters, photographs, and the company history. The series contains numerous proofs for advertisements which appeared in many prominent newspapers and magazines.
Series II: General Accounts ( 1853-1926) ) contains the general accounting records of the company. All the records in this series are in bound volumes. The series contains five groups of records: Day Books, Cash Books, Journals, Check Registers, and Ledgers.
Series III: Purchasing Records ( 1896-1926 ) contains the purchasing records of the company, all of which are in bound volumes. The series includes Expenditure Journals, Purchase Ledgers, and Purchase Sheets.
Series IV: Sales Records ( 1880-1935 ) contains the company sales records, all of which are in bound volumes. The records are organized in eight categories: Invoices, Sales Cash Books, Sales Journals, Sales Credits and Rebates, Sales Ledgers, Accounts Receivable, Customers by State, and Scrapbooks.
Series V: Labor Records ( 1884-1916 ) contains the company's labor records, all of which are in bound volumes. This series contains three types of records: Time Books, Payroll, and Medical Records.
Series VI: London Records ( 1885-1929 ) contains various records of the London, England division, all of which are in bound volumes. There are seven types of records: Cash Books, Ledgers and Sheets, Account Books, Discounts and Allowances, Sales and Stocks, Cash Sales Ledgers, and Sales Ledgers.
Custodial History
The J.B. Williams Company donated the records to the Historical Society of Glastonbury when the company closed its Connecticut facilities in 1960. The Historical Society of Glastonbury donated the records to the University of Connecticut in May 1967.
Acquisition Information
The J.B. Williams Company Records were donated to the University of Connecticut in May 1967.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to Connecticut businesses. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the Reading Room desk.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Location of Copies or Alternate Formats
Digital reproductions of materials in this collection may also be found in the Archives & Special Collections digital repository.
Financial Records; Fliers (printed matter); Photocopies; Publications (documents); Photographs; Administrative records; Men's toiletries; Toilet preparations industry; Notebooks; Glastonbury (inhabited place); New Jersey (state); Notes; Correspondence; Advertisements; Connecticut (state); Blueprints (reprographic copies).; Soap trade; United Kingdom (nation); Hygiene products; Press releases; Commerce; London (inhabited place); Williams family.
- Series I: Administrative Records, 1888-1956
  - Advertisements: correspondence, endorsements, and magazine samples, 1888-1898 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Advertisements: proofs, 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 2-5)
  - Annual reports, 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Annual sales meeting newsletter: Swampscott News and Glastonbury Bugle, 1949-1952 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence
    - Census reports, 1900-1920 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Chamber of Commerce of the U.S., 1918 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Committee of Industrial Preparedness, 1914-1917 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - CT Commission of Public Welfare, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - CT Department of Labor, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - CT State Council of Defense, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Federal Trade Commission, 1916-1928 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Industrial inventory for Army and Navy, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Manufacturers' organizations, 1918-1928 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - New England Fuel Administration, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - U.S. Department of Agriculture, 1917-1918 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - U.S. Department of Commerce, 1919-1928 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - U.S. Department of the Interior, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - U.S. Employment Services, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - U.S. Food Administration, 1917-1918 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - U.S. Fuel Administration, 1918-1919 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - U.S. Geological Survey, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - U.S. War Department, 1918-1919 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - U.S. War Industries Board, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - U.S. War Trade Board, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - History: J.B. Williams Company, 1818-1960 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - History: J.B. Williams family genealogy, 1638-1938 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Merger proposal: McKesson plan, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Publicity items, building dimensions, computations, others, 1907-1925 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Monthly newsletter: Shavings, 1943-1952 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Photographs: buildings, staff, products, 1928-1948 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Scrapbook, 1876-1950 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Series II: General Accounts, 1853-1926
  - Day Books
    - 1875 January - 1878 April (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - 1878 April - 1881 January (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - 1881 January - 1883 August (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - 1883 August - 1889 February (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - Cash Books
    - 1853 February - 1860 February (Box 8, Folder 36)
    - 1860 February - 1867 February (Box 9, Folder 37)
    - 1867 February - 1874 January (Box 10, Folder 38)
    - 1874 January - 1881 December (Box 11, Folder 39)
    - 1881 January - 1889 February (Box 12, Folder 40)
    - 1885 January - 1888 August (Box 13, Folder 41)
    - 1888 September - 1891 August (Box 14, Folder 42)
    - 1891 August - 1893 October (Box 15, Folder 43)
    - 1893 November - 1895 September (Box 16, Folder 44)
    - 1895 September - 1895 December (Box 17, Folder 45)
    - 1896 January - 1899 December (Box 18, Folder 46)
    - 1899 December - 1902 November (Box 19, Folder 47)
  - Daily Cash Balance, 1903 May - 1906 Jun (Box 20, Folder 48)
  - Cash Book, 1906 June - 1909 May (Box 21, Folder 49)
  - General Cash, 1910 July - 1913 July (Box 22, Folder 50)
  - Cash Book, 1920 July - 1921 November (Box 23, Folder 51)
  - Journals
    - 1850 May - 1853 March (Box 24, Folder 52)
    - 1853 March - 1856 May (Box 25, Folder 53)
    - 1856 February - 1859 December (Box 26, Folder 54)
    - 1859 December - 1863 October (Box 27, Folder 55)
    - 1863 October - 1867 August (Box 28, Folder 56)
    - 1867 August - 1870 March (Box 29, Folder 57)
    - 1871 February - 1874 July (Box 30, Folder 58)
    - 1885 January - 1887 December (Box 31, Folder 59)
    - 1887 December - 1890 December (Box 32, Folder 60)
    - 1890 August - 1892 December (Box 33, Folder 61)
    - 1892 December - 1894 August (Box 34, Folder 62)
    - 1894 August - 1898 December (Box 35, Folder 63)
    - 1896 January - 1898 April (Box 36, Folder 64)
    - 1898 May - 1899 December (Box 37, Folder 65)
    - 1900 January - 1902 September (Box 38, Folder 66)
    - 1902 October - 1904 July (Box 39, Folder 67)
    - 1904 July - 1906 January (Box 40, Folder 68)
    - 1906 January - 1907 July (Box 41, Folder 69)
  - Check registers
    - 1902 December - 1904 March (Box 42, Folder 70)
    - 1904 March - 1905 November (Box 43, Folder 71)
    - 1905 November - 1907 July (Box 44, Folder 72)
    - 1907 July - 1909 January (Box 45, Folder 73)
    - 1909 January - 1910 May (Box 46, Folder 74)
    - 1910 May - 1911 August (Box 47, Folder 75)
    - 1911 August - 1919 December (Box 48, Folder 76)
    - 1919 December - 1926 January (Box 49, Folder 77)
    - 1926 June - 1926 November (Box 50, Folder 78)
  - Ledgers
    - 1846 October - 1851 (Box 51, Folder 79)
    - 1851 April - 1856 January (Box 52, Folder 80)
    - 1856-1864 (Box 53, Folder 81)
    - 1864-1868 (Box 54, Folder 82)
    - 1869-1880 (Box 55, Folder 83)
    - 1881-1885 (Box 56, Folder 84)
    - 1885-1888 (Box 57, Folder 85)
    - 1887-1888 (Box 58, Folder 86)
    - 1887-1888 (Box 59, Folder 87)
    - 1889-1892 (Box 60, Folder 88)
    - 1893-1895 (Box 61, Folder 89)
    - 1903 (Box 62, Folder 90)
  - Trial Balance Ledger, 1886-1887 (Box 63, Folder 91)
  - Index to ledger, undated (Box 64, Folder 92)
- Series III: Purchasing Records, 1896-1926
  - Expenditure journals
    - 1921-1924 (Box 65, Folder 93)
    - 1925 - 1926 (Box 66, Folder 94)
  - Purchase ledgers
    - Index, 1896 - 1899 (Box 67, Folder 95)
    - 1896-1899 (Box 68, Folder 96)
    - 1900-1901 (Box 69, Folder 97)
    - 1904-1909 (Box 70, Folder 98)
  - Purchase sheets
    - 1915 January - 1924 December (Box 71, Folder 99)
    - 1925 January - 1926 December (Box 72, Folder 100)
- Series IV: Sales Records, 1880-1935
  - Invoices
    - 1880 February - 1885 January (Box 73, Folder 101)
    - 1886 October - 1887 May (Box 74, Folder 102)
    - 1887 May - 1887 December (Box 75, Folder 103)
    - 1887 December - 1888 July (Box 76, Folder 104)
    - 1888 July - 1889 February (Box 77, Folder 105)
    - 1889 February - 1889 August (Box 78, Folder 106)
    - 1889 August - 1890 June (Box 79, Folder 107)
    - 1890 January - 1890 April (Box 80, Folder 108)
    - 1890 April - 1890 August (Box 81, Folder 109)
    - 1890 August - 1890 November (Box 82, Folder 110)
    - 1890 November - 1891 March (Box 83, Folder 111)
    - 1891 March - 1891 July (Box 84, Folder 112)
    - 1891 July (Box 85, Folder 113)
  - Sales cash books
    - 1896 January - 1899 January (Box 86, Folder 114)
    - 1899 January - 1899 December (Box 87, Folder 115)
    - 1900 January - 1902 April (Box 88, Folder 116)
    - 1902 April - 1904 April (Box 89, Folder 117)
    - 1904 April - 1905 April (Box 90, Folder 118)
    - 1905 December - 1907 January (Box 91, Folder 119)
    - 1907 January - 1908 September (Box 92, Folder 120)
    - 1908 September - 1909 April (Box 93, Folder 121)
    - 1919 May - 1920 May (Box 94, Folder 122)
    - 1910 May - 1910 December (Box 95, Folder 123)
  - Sales Journals
    - 1885 January - 1888 April (Box 96, Folder 124)
    - 1888 May - 1891 July (Box 97, Folder 125)
    - 1891 August - 1891 October (Box 98, Folder 126)
    - 1891 October - 1892 February (Box 99, Folder 127)
    - 1892 February - 1892 May (Box 100, Folder 128)
    - 1892 May - 1892 August (Box 101, Folder 129)
    - 1892 August - 1892 November (Box 102, Folder 130)
    - 1892 November - 1893 January (Box 103, Folder 131)
    - 1893 January - 1893 April (Box 104, Folder 132)
    - 1893 April - 1893 July (Box 105, Folder 133)
    - 1893 July - 1893 October (Box 106, Folder 134)
    - 1893 October - 1894 January (Box 107, Folder 135)
    - 1894 January - 1894 March (Box 108, Folder 136)
    - 1894 March - 1894 June (Box 109, Folder 137)
    - 1894 June - 1894 August (Box 110, Folder 138)
    - 1894 August - 1894 October (Box 111, Folder 139)
    - 1894 October - 1895 January (Box 112, Folder 140)
    - 1895 January - 1895 April (Box 113, Folder 141)
    - 1895 April - 1895 June (Box 114, Folder 142)
    - 1895 June - 1895 September (Box 115, Folder 143)
    - 1895 September - 1895 November (Box 116, Folder 144)
    - 1895 November - 1896 February (Box 117, Folder 145)
    - 1896 February - 1896 April (Box 118, Folder 146)
    - 1896 April - 1896 July (Box 119, Folder 147)
    - 1896 July - 1896 October (Box 120, Folder 148)
    - 1896 October - 1896 December (Box 121, Folder 148)
    - 1896 December - 1897 February (Box 122, Folder 150)
    - 1897 February - 1897 May (Box 123, Folder 151)
    - 1897 May - 1897 July (Box 124, Folder 152)
    - 1897 July - 1897 September (Box 125, Folder 153)
    - 1897 September - 1897 November (Box 126, Folder 154)
    - 1897 November - 1898 February (Box 127, Folder 155)
    - 1898 February - 1898 April (Box 128, Folder 156)
    - 1898 April - 1898 July (Box 129, Folder 157)
    - 1898 July - 1898 September (Box 130, Folder 158)
    - 1898 September - 1898 November (Box 131, Folder 159)
    - 1898 November - 1899 February (Box 132, Folder 160)
    - 1899 February - 1899 April (Box 133, Folder 161)
    - 1899 April - 1899 June (Box 134, Folder 162)
    - 1899 June - 1899 August (Box 135, Folder 163)
    - 1899 August - 1899 October (Box 136, Folder 164)
    - 1899 October - 1899 December (Box 137, Folder 165)
    - 1899 December - 1900 March (Box 138, Folder 166)
    - 1900 March - 1900 June (Box 139, Folder 167)
    - 1900 June - 1900 August (Box 140, Folder 168)
    - 1900 August - 1900 November (Box 141, Folder 169)
    - 1900 November - 1901 February (Box 142, Folder 170)
    - 1901 February - 1901 May (Box 143, Folder 171)
    - 1901 May - 1901 July (Box 144, Folder 172)
    - 1901 July - 1901 October (Box 145, Folder 173)
    - 1901 October - 1901 December (Box 146, Folder 174)
    - 1901 December - 1902 March (Box 147, Folder 175)
    - 1902 March - 1902 May (Box 148, Folder 176)
    - 1902 May - 1902 July (Box 149, Folder 177)
    - 1902 July - 1902 October (Box 150, Folder 178)
    - 1902 October - 1902 November (Box 151, Folder 179)
    - 1900 January - 1900 August (Box 152, Folder 180)
    - 1900 August - 1901 March (Box 153, Folder 181)
    - 1901 March - 1901 September (Box 154, Folder 182)
    - 1901 September - 1902 March (Box 155, Folder 183)
    - 1902 March - 1902 October (Box 156, Folder 184)
    - 1903 December - 1912 September (Box 157, Folder 185)
  - Sales Credits and Rebates
    - 1899 October - 1903 January (Box 158, Folder 186)
    - 1893 (Box 159, Folder 187)
    - 1894 (Box 160, Folder 188)
    - 1895 (Box 161, Folder 189)
    - 1896 (Box 162, Folder 190)
    - 1897 (Box 163, Folder 191)
    - 1898 (Box 164, Folder 192)
  - Sales Ledgers
    - 1896 (Box 165, Folder 193)
    - 1897 (Box 166, Folder 194)
    - 1896 (Box 167, Folder 195)
    - 1897 (Box 168, Folder 196)
    - 1898 (Box 169, Folder 197)
    - 1899 (Box 170, Folder 198)
    - 1899 December - 1902 March (Box 171, Folder 199)
    - 1899 December - 1903 June (Box 172, Folder 200)
    - 1900 August - 1902 December (Box 173, Folder 201)
    - 1902 December - 1904 December (Box 174, Folder 202)
    - 1902-1904 (Box 175, Folder 203)
    - 1904 (Box 176, Folder 204)
    - 1911-1918 (Box 177, Folder 205)
    - 1909-1919 (Box 178, Folder 206)
    - 1909-1919 (Box 179, Folder 207)
    - 1909-1919 (Box 180, Folder 208)
    - 1909-1919 (Box 181, Folder 209)
    - 1912-1919 (Box 182, Folder 210)
    - 1913 April - 1914 March (Box 183, Folder 211)
    - 1914-1919 (Box 184, Folder 212)
    - 1914-1919 (Box 185, Folder 213)
    - 1916-1918 (Box 186, Folder 214)
    - 1909-1920 (Box 187, Folder 215)
    - 1909-1919 (Box 188, Folder 216)
    - 1909-1919 (Box 189, Folder 217)
    - 1909-1919 (Box 190, Folder 218)
    - 1909-1919 (Box 191, Folder 219)
    - 1909-1919 (Box 192, Folder 220)
    - 1909-1919 (Box 193, Folder 221)
  - Accounts Receivable
    - 1906-1908 (Box 194, Folder 222)
  - Customers by State
    - 1900-1909 (Box 195, Folder 223)
  - Scrapbooks
    - 1897 May - 1904 August (Box 196, Folder 224)
    - 1904 September - 1908 September (Box 197, Folder 225)
    - 1926-1936 (Box 198, Folder 226)
- Series V: Labor Records, 1884-1916
  - Time Books
    - 1885 January - 1887 June (Box 199, Folder 226)
    - 1887 July - 1889 June (Box 200, Folder 227)
    - 1889 July - 1891 March (Box 201, Folder 228)
    - 1891 April - 1901 February (Box 202, Folder 229)
    - 1901-1903 (Box 203, Folder 230)
  - Payroll
    - 1901 March - 1903 October (Box 204, Folder 231)
    - 1904 January - 1904 September (Box 205, Folder 232)
    - 1912-1913 (Box 206, Folder 233)
    - 1914 January - 1916 August (Box 207, Folder 234)
  - Medical Journals
    - Dr. Kingsbury's Ledger, 1884-1893 (Box 208, Folder 235)
- Series VI: London Records, 1885-1929
  - Cash Books
    - 1909 April - 1911 April (Box 209, Folder 236)
    - 1911 May - 1913 May (Box 210, Folder 237)
  - Ledger and Sheets
    - 1885-1887 (Box 211, Folder 238)
    - 1893-1900 (Box 212, Folder 239)
    - 1901-1904 (Box 213, Folder 240)
    - 1904-1908 (Box 214, Folder 241)
    - 1908-1909 (Box 215, Folder 242)
    - 1910 January - 1911 December (Box 216, Folder 243)
    - 1923-1926 (Box 217, Folder 244)
    - 1926 July - 1926 December (Box 218, Folder 245)
    - 1926 December - 1927 June (Box 219, Folder 246)
    - 1927 June - 1927 December (Box 220, Folder 247)
    - 1928 January - 1928 July (Box 221, Folder 248)
    - 1928 July - 1928 November (Box 222, Folder 249)
    - 1928 December - 1929 October (Box 223, Folder 250)
  - Account Books
    - A - K, 1920-1923 (Box 224, Folder 251)
    - L - Z, 1920-1923 (Box 225, Folder 252)
  - Discounts and Allowances
    - A - B, 1920-1928 (Box 226, Folder 253)
    - C - E, 1923-1929 (Box 227, Folder 254)
    - F - G, 1923-1929 (Box 228, Folder 255)
    - H - M, 1923-1928 (Box 229, Folder 256)
    - N - Q, 1923-1928 (Box 230, Folder 257)
    - R - T, 1923-1928 (Box 231, Folder 258)
    - W - Y, 1923-1928 (Box 232, Folder 259)
    - Y - Z and foreign customers, 1923-1929 (Box 233, Folder 260)
  - Sales and Stock (Box 234, Folder 261)
  - Cash Sales Ledgers
    - 1902 December - 1910 March (Box 235, Folder 262)
  - Sales Ledgers
    - 1902-1905 (Box 236, Folder 263)
    - 1926 July - 1927 March (Box 237, Folder 264)
    - 1927 April - 1929 March (Box 237, Folder 265)
    - 1927 April - 1929 March (Box 237, Folder 266)
    - 1926 July - 1929 March (Box 238, Folder 267)
    - 1926 July - 1929 March (Box 238, Folder 268)
    - 1926 July - 1929 March (Box 239, Folder 269)
    - 1926 July - 1927 March (Box 240, Folder 270)
    - 1928 January - 1929 March (Box 241, Folder 271)
    - 1928 December - 1929 March
    - Miscellaneous sheets, 1927-1928